<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>P4 | Tomasz Osiński - blog &amp; personal site</title>
    <link>https://osinstom.github.io/tags/p4/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://osinstom.github.io/tags/p4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>P4</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://osinstom.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>P4</title>
      <link>https://osinstom.github.io/tags/p4/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>IP Router in P4</title>
      <link>https://osinstom.github.io/post/2019-10-22-ip-router-in-p4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://osinstom.github.io/post/2019-10-22-ip-router-in-p4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the previous post I introduced P4 and tools to implement network prototypes. Now, I would like to show a basic example how to use this tools in practice to run an experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prepared a demo of IP routing to show how simply someone can prototype a commonly used technology. The demo is based on P4 and Mininet. The source code and user guide is available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/osinstom/p4-demos/tree/master/ip-routing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/osinstom/p4-demos/tree/master/ip-routing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The README file contains a description of a P4 program&amp;rsquo;s design as well as a topology of a test network. Below I summarize a design choices that I made:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have used &lt;strong&gt;P4_16&lt;/strong&gt; as it is the newest version of P4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As the P4 target I use &lt;strong&gt;BMv2&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/p4lang/behavioral-model&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/p4lang/behavioral-model&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;P4_16&lt;/strong&gt; introduces the concept of architecture model for target device. I have used &lt;strong&gt;V1Model&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/p4lang/p4c/blob/master/p4include/v1model.p4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://github.com/p4lang/p4c/blob/master/p4include/v1model.p4&lt;/a&gt;), which is a defualt one for BMv2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The V1Model forces us to implement the &lt;strong&gt;Ingress&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Egress&lt;/strong&gt; control blocks, &lt;strong&gt;Parser&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Deparser&lt;/strong&gt; and methods to handle checksum (verifyChecksum and computeChecksum). For the sake of demo I don&amp;rsquo;t focus on checksum operations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design choices for the &lt;strong&gt;router.p4&lt;/strong&gt; program:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I defined Ethernet and IPv4 headers (only)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I defined additional metadata struct called &lt;strong&gt;routing_metadata&lt;/strong&gt;. It is used to pass a routing decision made in the Ingress block to the Egress block. In the Egress block it will be used to determine the MAC address of the next-hop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Parser Logic handles only Ethernet and IPv4 headers (e.g. ARP, IPv6 or VLAN is not parsed)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the &lt;strong&gt;Ingress&lt;/strong&gt; control we defined the &lt;strong&gt;routing_table&lt;/strong&gt;. This table has three actions: drop(), NoAction() and ipv4_forward(). The last action performs three operations:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it selects output port based on the IPv4 destination LPM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it sets a next-hop IP address in routing_metadata.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it decrements TTL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the &lt;strong&gt;Egress&lt;/strong&gt; control block we defined &lt;strong&gt;switching_table&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;mac_rewriting_table&lt;/strong&gt;. The switching_table sets a destination MAC for packet based on next-hop IP from routing_metadata. The mac_rewriting_table changes the source MAC address for packet according to port, that has been selected as the output port.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to know basics of how P4 works I encourage you to follow a user guide and test how IP routing written in P4 works. In the subsequent posts I will show another example - MPLS network written in P4.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
