<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Python on Tomasz Osiński - blog &amp; personal site</title>
    <link>https://osinstom.github.io/tags/python/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Python on Tomasz Osiński - blog &amp; personal site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>{year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://osinstom.github.io/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The MPLS network based on P4</title>
      <link>https://osinstom.github.io/post/2019-10-22-mpls-network-p4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://osinstom.github.io/post/2019-10-22-mpls-network-p4/</guid>
      <description>The MPLS network based on P4 In the previous post I described the implementation of the IP router in the P4 language. Now, I would like to move to a little bit more advanced technology - MPLS (Multi Protocol Label Switching). This post describes the demo of MPLS implemented in P4. The demo is avaiable on my GitHub. Note that the demo is just a Proof of Concept and the scenario may differ from the way how MPLS works in a real-world network.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network prototyping made easy with P4 and Python!</title>
      <link>https://osinstom.github.io/post/2019-10-22-network-prototyping-made-easy-with-p4-and-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://osinstom.github.io/post/2019-10-22-network-prototyping-made-easy-with-p4-and-python/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Have you ever tried to understand deeply mechanisms of network protocols? I mean network protocols used by computer networks like, for example, Internet Protocol (IP), Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) or Spanning Tree Protocol (STP). Students are taught at unversity how network systems works. Nextly, they become network administrators, developers or architects. They know how to configure network devices, design complex systems or develop network algorithms. However, it is likely that they got their knowledge from books and/or administration courses, not from development practice!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>